[Music]
Stanford
University um this goes back to particle
physics it's a bit off the subject to
class but there's evidence that the
neutrinos have math and they mix MH in a
particle physics class we didn't address
mixing and I but I wanted to ask if the
neutrinos if they have a mass must they
have the same
mass no they don't have all the same
mass
so then the question be how on Earth
next and conserve
energy well okay
um what it really means is that the mass
is energy right okay the igen states of
energy are linear
superpositions of the igen states of
something else that something else is
called uh the type of
nutrino so the igen states of
energy don't
mix the igen states of energy do not mix
with each
other uh and um it's just that the igen
states themselves are mixtures of
different uh different states there are
many many examples like
this in quantum mechanics
um a simple example is if you have a
potential which looks like
this this is the phenomenon of mixing in
a particular
context um supposing you have a particle
that uh moves in a potential that looks
like this all right so the particle can
be on this side and let's suppose for
the sake of argument that the barrier in
between the two um Minima is pretty
large large enough that uh that to a
good
approximation we might want to say that
the particle is either trapped on this
side or trapped on this side okay and
can't get
through now of course Quantum
mechanically there's a little bit of
possibility of leaking through the
barrier it's called
tunneling uh but supposing we ignore
that to begin with then we could just
take the leftand side here treat it as
though the right hand side didn't exist
as though there was an infinite barrier
preventing the particle from going
through you could think of this as a
brick
wall this is a brick wall and uh
ordinary particles don't go through
brick walls very easily so it's a good
approximation just to Pretend This is
infinitely high and in that case you
would ask what is the ground state what
is the ground state wave function and
ground state energy of the system and
you might say well okay let's just
forget the fact that that this part is
over here the ground state looks like
that it's some wave function it has no
nodes no zeros as smooth as possible and
it has some energy
e but wait a minute if this potential is
exactly symmetric then there must be
another ground state on this
side another ground state on that side
which has exactly the same energy same
energy same profile except it's on the
other side of the barrier and in every
way is identical these are two distinct
states which apparently have exactly the
same energy but they don't they don't
and the reason
is that these wave functions are not
exactly igen states of the energy now
here's what we know we know that for a
potential like
this the igen states of energy are
either symmetric or anti-symmetric
functions this is a theorem about
quantum mechanics it's a theorem about
differential
equations if the potential is symmetric
then the wave
functions which are the energy igen
states are either symmetric or
anti-symmetric what does anti-symmetric
mean it means that uh that when you
cross over the dividing barrier between
here it goes from positive to
negative okay so let's see if we can
understand better what's really going
on um each one of these wave functions
to begin with is neither symmetric nor
anti-symmetric there's one over here and
there's another one over here and it's
neither symmetric this doesn't look very
symmetric symmetric
means that uh it is invariant with
respect to reflection about the the uh
the origin here symmetric would mean
that if you reflect it it stays the same
well this is certainly not symmetric if
you reflect it you get a wave function
over
here so this is neither symmetric nor
anti- symmetric neither is the other
one okay but you can make symmetric and
anti-symmetric
combinations for
example if I take a wave function which
looks very much almost exactly like that
gets very small in between where the
potential energy is very large can't get
into there or it can but only a tiny
little bit and then continue it
symmetrically on the other side that
doesn't look very symmetric I
apologize but uh it's supposed to be
symmetric then this wave function would
have a slightly lower
energy
than either a wave function restricted
to this side or to this side
you can lower the energy now how much
would lower the energy a tiny tiny
amount an exponentially small amount but
the energy of the symmetric wave
function would be
slightly less than the energy of either
one of
these okay that's the first state the
ground state the true ground state the
true energy igen state is this
combination here the next excited state
looks like
this it looks almost exactly the same oh
incidentally remember that the sign of
the wave function is immaterial to
anything if you have a wave function and
it's an igen state of some operator if
you change the sign of the wave function
it's still uh an igen Vector of the same
quantity the sign of the wave function
doesn't contain any real
information okay okay
so what is the first excited state the
theorem is that the first excited state
always has one node given the symmetry
of the problem and so forth the only
node everybody know what a node
is means a place where the wave function
is
zero okay if it's anti-symmetric it
surely has a node it can't be
anti-symmetric and not have a node and
if what does a wave function look like
it looks like almost exactly the same
thing on this side likewise on this side
except that it's
negative like that so over the region
where the wave function is
appreciable it looks exactly the same on
this side and on the right hand side it
looks exactly the same except that it uh
that it's
negative this energy is ever so slightly
larger than the energy of just one of
these
waves if it were constrained to live on
one side so what
happens is originally before we took
into
account the the fact that the barrier is
not infinitely
high before we took that into account we
basically had two energy levels let's
draw energy energy here two energy
levels the one on the left and the one
on the right and they were at exactly
the same energy but not quite of
course now we took into
account the fact that the wave functions
can leak through the barrier a little
bit that's just the fact that it doesn't
quite go to zero here it's almost zero
very close to zero but not quite the
effect of that is to split these two
energies a little
bit it splits the two energies but gives
you wave functions which are
not like the original one-sided wave
functions the one-sided wave functions
which would have
been what you would have if you really
had an infinite barrier in between get
mixed they get mixed from left-sided and
right sided to left-sided plus right
sided and left-sided minus right
sided basically that's what's going on
you have two states
the left side and the right
side neither one is exactly an energy
igen State and the real energy igen
states are mixtures of the two of
them
um the mixtures of the two of them with
slightly different
energy what's the consequence of the
fact that there that the wave functions
are these MI mixtures it's neither left
nor right but 1 / < TK of two left plus
1un of two right and 1 overun of two
left minus 1/ < TK of two right those
are the two um igen states of the
energy okay
so now let's try to find out what would
happen if
we
started if we put an electron an
electron a particle if we put an
electron on the right hand on the left
hand side we start with an electron on
the left hand side what happens how does
it evolve so we can work this out let's
say we have two wave functions one of
them is s left plus
cite and this is an igen state of energy
with slightly less
energy let's say the energy of this
is
E1 E1 is every so slightly less than the
energy if you couldn't get through the
barrier and then you have that's the
that's that's the uh let's call it E1
minus
Epsilon in other
words when the two wave functions mix
the energy is lowered for the symmetric
State and for the anti-symmetric State
there should be a square root of two
here and then we have S left minus s
right over Square < TK of
two and that has an
energy
E1 plus Epsilon it just shifted up a
little
bit okay now each one of these is an
igen state of the energy that means that
if you were to follow its time
dependence it would
dependence if you were to solve the
Schrodinger there time dependence
rotinger equation what would be the time
dependence of this
one e to the
I
E1 minus Epsilon T
right okay
now what about this one
this one has e to the
I E1 plus Epsilon
T okay now let's
start with s left let's call this let's
give this a name let's call this S Plus
and let's call this s
minus S Plus and S
minus but now I'm interested not in s
plus plus plus I minus I know exactly
what happens to either of those but I'm
interested in what happens if I start
with pure s left somebody just plopped a
uh a particle into the left hand well
here how does it evolve so that means
that at time T equals 0 we start with
just s left at T equals
0 we start
with just s left but s left
is equal this is at time t equal 0 so we
can set that t is equal to Z that's
equal to S plus plus I
minus over Square < TK of
two we get that just by adding these two
the S wres cancel and if we're careful
about it we'll find there's a 1/ < TK of
two
there so that's the initial State sorry
so I s
minus s+ plus s minus over < TK 2 is s
left so this is the initial state but
how does it evolve what happens to it
with time with time each one of these
picks up its own phase so after a Time T
the wave function is no longer just s
left let's write it down what it is it's
S
Plus times e to the I E1 minus Epsilon
T that's what happens to S 1 or S Plus
excuse me that's what happens to S Plus
and what happens to S minus that's
plus s
minus E to the minus
I
E1 I guess it's plus oh no e to the plus
E1 plus Epsilon
T did I get the sign of the exponent
right I did not it's should be
minus it doesn't matter doesn't make any
difference just leave it doesn't make
any difference okay so first of all we
can factor out an overall Factor e to
the I
E1
T that factors out from both of them and
then we get
s+ e e to the minus I Epsilon
t plus s minus E to the + I Epsilon
T over Square < TK of
two okay what happens to this with
time with time these phases are
different notice that one of them goes
as e to the minus I Epsilon T the other
goes as e to the plus I Epsilon
T what's going to happen we started out
only with s
left we wrote it in terms of S Plus and
S minus and now we let it evolve with
time after an appropriate amount of time
the sign of these two will be opposite
to each other how long does that take
how long does it take these are two
different complex numbers how long and
think about it this
way there points on the complex plane on
the unit circle one of them is slowly
drifting
up on the unit circle e to plus I
Epsilon T the other one is drifting down
it takes a certain amount of
time before the first one is up on the
top and the second one is down on the
bottom should we figure out how long
that takes let's figure out how long
that
takes all right where we want to know
how long does it take for this to become
equal to minus that so let's just write
it down e to the minus I Epsilon t equal
minus e to+ i Epsilon
[Music]
T Let's uh just multiply by uh what does
it say this says that e to the 2 I
Epsilon t =
minus1 i just multiply both sides by e
to the E to plus I Epsilon T I get e to
2 I Epsilon T here and on the left side
I get one but there's a minus sign okay
how long does it
take before this thing is equal to
minus1 well minus1 is e to the e to the
I PI right e to the I Pi so the time
must be
twice Epsilon T =
Pi a twice Epsilon
T equals
Pi then we're in this situation where
the two phases here have opposite
sign by the time that
happens this wave function has become
proportional to the wave function with a
minus sign
here all right there is an e to 2 I EP
on T on the outside but that's not
interesting what was originally a plus
sign evolves into a minus sign because
the two phases are not the because the
energies are slightly different the two
phases are getting out of phase and
after a while they become opposite well
when S
Plus when it becomes s plus minus s
minus we go back to here s+ minus s
minus is s
right
just look at it take the difference s
plus minus s right s minus s minus the S
lefts cancel and we get just the S right
term so that means after this amount of
time which if Epsilon is small can be a
very long time if Epsilon is small then
this time is very small but after that
amount of time if you were to look the
particle would be on the other
side it would have materialized on the
other side gone through the barrier and
materialized on the other
side that's what this
says Okay so the phenomenon of mixing
goes together with the phenomenon of
oscillations this will go on and on and
on
after when
um okay so tce in in another
corresponding
interval it'll swing back swing back and
forth and back and forth and
oscillate so it looks like you're
getting oscillations between one wave
function in the other that's correct you
are well between the two sides it's not
violating energy the energy igen states
are doing what they're supposed to do
each one evolves separately
but if you start with a thing which is
not an energy igen state it will also do
what non-energy igen states are supposed
to do it will evolve and it will evolve
back and forth from one to the other
neutrinos behave like
that
uh the analog of the left wave function
is the
neutrino which is made it's not it's not
made on the left it's made by the decay
of of
Decay uh involving an electron decay of
of a particle that involves an electron
and it's called the electron
neutrino uh the same precise kind of
Decay if it decayed into instead of an
electron a me particle it would make
a uh a mu
neutrino the real igen state of the
energy of the mass is kind of a linear
is a linear combination of the electron
and the muon neutrino which is entirely
analogous uh to the two states S Plus
and S
minus but when an electron when a
nutrino is made it's made either in a
Decay involving an electron or in a
Decay involving a muon if it's made in a
Decay involving an electron it's like
plunking the particle into the left well
here if if it's made in a Decay that
involves the muon it's like plunking the
state into the right well but if you
wait a while it'll just go back and
forth between them now that's
interesting because an
electron which is
created sorry a nutrino which is of the
electron
type can undergo
processes other kinds of process
processes not just these decays
scattering processes in which it
produces an electron will not produce a
muon an electron nutrino will not
produce a muon and a muon nutrino will
not produce an electron so here's the
experiment you start with an electron
nutrino you wait a while half a period
like this again and it becomes a muon
nutrino and once it's become a muon
nutrino you let it interact with
something and see if it produces is an
electron or a
muon okay so if you create this electron
sorry this
muon this
neutrino as an electron
neutrino and then you just let it go a
little bit you know you don't let it go
very far very long well if it was
produced here it sort of stays here so
after a little bit you do your
experiment and you discover the electron
neutrino only makes electrons
only interacts in such a way as to make
electrons the muon nutrino only
interacts in ways such as to make a muon
but if you have a long Baseline so that
the nutrino can go a long
ways long enough that it under goes one
of these oscillations an electron
nutrino made somewhere if you go down
line far enough you'll you'll Discover
it can make
muons likewise the muon matrino and in
an oscillating way if you have a very
long Baseline you would discover that
there are oscillations
um uh of the neutrino from one type to
the
other question what determines the size
of
Epsilon oh well all sorts of details
such as the mass of the particle the
height of the potential the width of the
barrier it's extremely
sensitive exponentially sensitive to um
to the parameters of the
barrier has this been observed
absolutely both in neutrinos and in um
tunneling things like
this is that connected at all to nutrino
Mass the nutrino masses are the energy
levels now they they start out with very
very small energies to begin with but
then the mixing between them splits the
energies a little bit so they start out
with small Energies
but then even on top of that there's a
little bit of splitting and uh so the
prevailing wisdom is that the tree know
that matter oh absolutely not wisdom
it's an experimental
fact
yeah if this were saying ammonia
molecule that barrier would be represent
it's switching through the plane but
what does that barrier represent when
you have well okay the um I carry what's
the ammonia is that a tetrahedron what's
it's tetrahedron yeah okay let
find uh well the only reason I say
tetrahedron is because a tetrahedron is
an obvious one to have a tunneling
process tetrahedron has um four
atoms one two three what is
ammonia what is
it NH
h44 you're telling me it has five
atoms NH H3 so it has three three h
atoms I assume that's what an H3 means
I'm not a very good chemist and then it
has
a nooi or whatever it's called
Uh so there's a
triangle and then up above the triangle
is the
tetrahedral nitrogen nitrogen must be
nitrogen yeah
right okay now the the uh the the the
the molecular bonds are such that This n
That this I'm going to call it a
neutrino please help
me it's not a nutrino it's
nitrogen this nitrogen likes to sit a
certain height above the base of the
triangle there meaning to say its energy
is lowest when it's up here but of
course there's another state which is
symmetric where the um nitrogen is down
below here and the point is you can
tunnel from one to the other in exactly
the same way so tunneling from one to
the other is basically the nitrogen
tunneling through the through the plane
of the hydrogen or something like that
um question was you can see
phally the barri is in Amon
what barri between el oh oh oh oh oh no
no that's uh there's no barrier there's
just a
no no no it's more than an analogy um
the
uh
[Music]
um there's coupling in the
hamiltonian which for whatever reason
nobody knows why but there's coupling in
the hamiltonian which takes an electron
nutrino to a muon nutrino and vice
versa uh in this case the there's no cup
there's a there's a coupling and the
coupling is due to the tunneling process
this is basically the same mathematics
but um I'll tell you where else you've
seen this well you've seen the same
thing and it's also a good example same
the mathematics is the same
um if you
take a yeah take a spin just a spin
we've done spins uh little you know
magnetic spin
electron without any magnetic field the
two states let's call them up and down
have the same energy up and down have
the the same
energy has energy
e and down has energy
e the energy would be just MC squ for
the electron let's say
all right now you put a little magnetic
field
on let's say the magnetic field is
pointing upward a weak magnetic
field what happens to the energy of
these two these are little magnets if
you like the little
magnets magnet is either up or down and
depending on the direction of the
magnetic field the up magnet will have a
slightly different energy than the down
magnet takes some work to to turn the
the thing over so the up electron and
the down electron will have slightly
different
energy
okay
um the up electron and the down elect oh
no no no no let's do something
else yeah let's put let's a little
different let's actually make the
um the magnetic field along the x
axis
let's put them the magnetic field along
the
x-axis then what are the igen states of
energy for the
system are they up and
down they're what we called left and
right remember when we studied spins
they're what we called the electron
pointing along the x-axis or the anti-
xaxis but the electron pointing along
the x-axis
is just a linear combination of the
electron being up or down same exact
kind of
combination let's call it
left I love this I like the red is this
is this visible yeah okay left is equal
to 1 / < TK 2 up plus
down likewise right is of the same sort
of thing the other equation there now
when I put put a little bit of magnetic
field
on the
result is energy IG states which are
left and right but with slightly
different energy why is the energy
slightly different well because
depending on which way the electron is
oriented it's either oriented along the
magnetic field or opposite to the
magnetic field so we have the same
situation where um there's a slight
splitting of the energy level
what's the result if we were to start
the electron up let's suppose we start
the electron up somebody gave us an up
electron and said here do with it what
you
want but it's in this very weak magnetic
field what happens to it you
remember it
processes it processes so after a
certain half period it becomes a down
after another half period it becomes an
up same same exact phenomena the energy
igen states are mixtures of up and down
and because of that there are up down
oscillations if there was some reason
why an electron liked to be made in a
certain experiment pointing along the up
Direction then if you waited a little
while it would be along the down
Direction so it's the same phenomena but
it doesn't require any tunneling it's
just the term and the hamiltonian which
mixes the up and down in this case the
magnetic field What happened to the
oh it also gets mixed in
there it also gets mixed in yeah so it's
the analog of having three states which
all get mixed with each other a little
more complicated because spin comes into
it but this is the basic
phenomenon
yeah and uh you know if you um you
you're probably quite capable of
understanding it now it uh you you know
enough to to read a paper or two from on
it I have a good question so in this
case when you mentioned that it it
processes if we look at it a tiny time
after we put the magnetic field we still
find it in the opposition or with a tiny
probability to being in the down will it
ever be towards us uh yeah it will yeah
yeah it will it'll process around
here so going from up to
down so it will not have just up or down
it could be in and out and it can be in
and out it will never if you start it up
it will not get along the x-axis it will
stay perpendicular to the x-axis so it's
a continuous on this Thea quite
continuous these phases just evolve
continuously but of course if you look
at it depending on what you're measuring
let's say you're measuring up or down
you'll either find up or down you won't
find anything in between but the
interesting thing is if you make the
electron in an upway
and you waight exactly a half in Period
like this you'll find it definitely down
so if there's something that a down
electron can do that an up electron
can't do and let's say something that an
up electron can do and a down electron
can't do you can do an experiment uh
which you create the up electron by
doing one kind of interaction and then
at a later time ask whether it's
behaving like the down electron the and
of course this is easy easy to do much
harder to do for
neutrinos said
it well is that why you specified a weak
weak field no no no it's got nothing to
do with the weakness of the field the
only reason I say a weak field is
because I don't want it to process very
rapidly if I want it to be anything like
the nutrino
situation where the oscillations are
very slow I will want to make a weak
field the uh the magnitude of the field
only only determines the period of the
oscillation and the analog of the field
itself is the strength of the mixing
between the different kinds of neutrinos
and that's that's simply and as far as
we know now it's just a
parameter it's a parameter in our Theory
and we don't know with any confidence
where it came from it's a very small
parameter
uh the electron masses are tiny to begin
with and the splittings between them are
obviously no bigger than the than the
masses of the bigger the ma the mass of
the nutrino
itself and so they're tiny numbers and
what their origin is is
uncertain what is true is that in the
standard model of elementary particle
physics there is no room for that
parameter that parameter is
mathematically um
forbidden in the absolutely standard
theory of particle physics meaning the
the standard
model
so where it comes from is some violation
of the standard model but it's very
small so it could be a very remote
phenomena remote in energy remote in
distance scales and so forth it probably
is okay um quick question yeah is the
only reason that people think the has
mass because it just it does change the
oscillation the oscillation is that the
only reason
MH other than theoretical uh
you right because of the
relativity couldn't change if it was
that's right that's right that's right
if it was truly massless it couldn't
change time dilation is right
you you could do experiments where you
detect whether it's in or out as well as
up or down you can do any experiment you
want but um
the if yeah
you right the polarization of the
electron in other words the direction of
the
spin doesn't tell you what value you
would measure except that if it's known
to be up and you measure upness or down
this you get up and does not tell you if
you measure the X component whether
you'll get plus or minus and it doesn't
tell you whether if you multiply measure
the Y component so the idea is to put it
in a known
configuration where if you measured the
upness down this you would get up and
then wait a half period until it's
pointing down and then measure it again
and you will definitely get
down that's the experiment after a
quarter period you'll definitely get
towards you yeah yeah if you waited a
half period to do the experiment with a
nutrino you would get 50% probability of
it acting like a me neutrino 50% like an
electr correct that would be a quarter
period quarter period yeah
um it's I don't the answer is no but for
reasons that are somewhat incidental it
is a little more complicated the
complications of spin get into it and
the oscillations are not exactly
symmetrical about the two but that's a
that's a
refinement the basic physics is
this so um yeah since the neutrino mass
is very and say you were looking at a
neutrino coming from the Sun to us to
preserve or conserve the momentum is the
velocity changing as it
oscillates yeah the velocity
um yeah let's see the velocity must
change yeah yeah you know the momentum
stays the same right and if the mass is
undergoing oscillations uh
right incidentally this is believed to
be the reason why there was a deficit of
solar
neutrinos for many
years there was a deficit of solar
neutrinos where not enough solar
neutrinos were seen on Earth to account
for the um for the expected number of uh
nutrino interactions taking place in the
Sun and of course the reason was that by
the time the neutrinos get here half of
them are unavailable to interact with
electrons or half of them or something
they're they've become muons or whatever
muon
neutros or some other
species all right well since we're
talking about
um these kinds of
things
uh I did read in the article that
somebody sent uh through the email that
the electron is a
sphere and I was a little bit surprised
to read
that I didn't I didn't think the
electron is a sphere and I still don't
think the electron is a sphere even
after reading the venerable um
Scientific
American so I thought I might uh since
has have people read that
article oh only one person read
it oh yeah it came in my mail I assumed
it came through the uh did did somebody
send
it maybe maybe it didn't come from any
of you maybe it came from
uh no it didn't come from Scientific
American question Chang
character okay so there's an article in
the Scientific American just for fun
just for fun let's uh let's uh I don't I
thought we' take a little bit of a break
at least for part of the hour tonight
and talk about
um real physical
phenomena not that the quantum field
theory is not a real physical phenomenon
but you know we've been concentrating on
the formal mathematics of
it is the electron a sphere what would
it mean for the electron to be a sphere
what does it mean for anything to be a
sphere a particle or an atom or whatever
else uh and what is it that was or
wasn't
measured that according to the author of
the Scientific American little blurb
there indicates that the electron is a
sphere and what does that say about uh
physics well first of all what was
measured is the electric dipole moment
of the
electron okay now we'll come to what
that means in a moment but I think you
all know what an electric dipole moment
is right if you have a little bit of
plus charge and a little bit of minus
charge and they're separated by distance
D then the dipole moment is just the
charge times the distance between them
and it represents a sort of off centered
charge
distribution the center of the dumbbell
let's think of it as a dumbbell the
center of the dumbbell is at the center
of the
dumbbell and an electric dipole would
indicate that there was an imbalance on
the two ends of the dipole of the
electric charge distribution that's what
an electric dipole
means for a thing not to have an
electric dipole does not first of all
does not say it's a
sphere um a charge distribution can have
many many different multipole moments
many many different shape parameters
okay what kind of shape corresponds to
having a dipole a situation exactly what
I said where there's an imbalance of
charge on one side relative to the other
side relative to some to some
Center what other the kinds of charge
distributions are they well you could
have a charge distribution shaped like
an oblate spheroid or a or any kind of
any kind of ellipsoid symmetric
ellipsoid non-symmetric ellipsoid any
kind of ellipsoid of that type would not
have a dipole moment that why not
because the
ellipsoid is symmetric about every axis
passing about every plane through
passing through the center if the charge
was uniformly distributed on the
ellipsoid there would be as much on the
top as on the bottom there would be as
much on the left as on the right and
there would be no dipole moment
what would you say about it would you
say it was a
sphere no you would say it has a
quadriple moment a quadripole moment is
the shape of a squashed sphere
ellipsoid it could also not even have a
quadripolar moment it could have an
octopolar moment that's a little bit
different kind of
thing uh an octopolar moment would be
free of dipole moment it would be free
of quadripole moment but it's not a
sphere
so in measuring the fact that an object
doesn't have an electric dipole moment
is not the evidence of any kind that
it's a sphere it's just an evidence that
it doesn't have an electric dipole
moment nothing more than that but when
you start to think about it in quantum
mechanics there's something funny about
the notion of spherical Symmetry and
things like that let's suppose we had
this
dumbbell but it's a quantum mechanical
dumbbell there are quantum mechanical
dumbbells some of my uh some of my um
colleagues
or I I didn't
see
um here's a quantum mechanical
dumbbell that's a molecule of some kind
a molecule with a bond that's more or
less fixed with two atoms okay two ATS
on either side
um let's take the ground St now that
doesn't look like a sphere it doesn't
look anything like a sphere right in
fact uh let's not worry about where its
charge is for a moment
um yeah we could put some charge let's
put some charge over here plus and
charge over here
minus okay now let's take the ground
state of that molecule
there're
two particles orbiting each
other how do you describe a state of the
molecule you describe the state of the
molecule by its angular
momentum angular momentum about the
center all of the states of this
molecule well of course there are also
vibrations but let's ignore the vi you
know radial vibrations but let's only
talk about the rotational States the
rotational states are characterized by
angular momentum
in general if the molecule is a boson
that means it has an even number of Fons
in it if it's a bon if the molecule has
integer spin then the ground state will
have what spin what angular
momentum zero sure the lowest energy
will be when the angular momentum is
zero but in quantum mechanics angular
momentum is the generator of rotations
what it says for a system to have
angular momentum zero is that its wave
function is completely symmetric with
respect to all rotations angular
momentum zero states are all
rotationally symmetric so quite
independently of what the charge
distribution might look like the quantum
mechanical state is rotationally
symmetric now you could say well that
just means it's a dumbbell all right but
it's just a dumbbell in a superposition
of states
which is
um symmetrized so that the probability
distribution for the electric charge is
completely rotationally symmetric does
that have a dipole moment or doesn't it
you call that having a dipole moment or
or doesn't it have a dipole moment well
you say okay let's take a snapshot of it
let's not uh worry about Quantum
superpositions and all that sort of
stuff let's take just take a quick
snapshot of it
the look even what I'm saying here would
even be true for the kind of dumbbell
that you would get in a gym if you
really got it down to the absolute
ground state which you can never do of
course the energy levels are so closely
spaced but if you got it down to the
absolute ground state state in
infinitely empty St space that the wave
function of that dumbbell would be
completely rotationally
symmetric so now comes a question do you
are you willing to call that a sphere a
spherical charge distribution or is it
just a lopsided charge distribution with
a probability distribution or a wave
function uh which is symmetrized
it okay the answer is ambiguous the
answer is ambiguous depending on the
kind of experiment that you do if you
took a sudden quick snapshot of it you
would discover that it has a lopsided
charge distribution right but you could
ask how fast does the camera have to be
in order to detect that it wasn't
smeared over the sphere how fast what is
the time resolution that's necessary and
the answer is it's not too hard to
figure out let's suppose you took a
quick snapshot of this is a measurement
a snapshot means a measurement and
basically the snapshot is measuring the
angle of the um of the molecule or the
the dumbbell you take a quick snapshot
and you measure the angle well if you
measure the angle a measurement of
something leaves the system in an igen
state of that something when you measure
something you kick it into an IG state
of the thing you measured so it may have
started in an IG state of angular
momentum you measure it and all of a
sudden it's in a state of definite
orientation
is a state of definite orientation does
it have a definite angular
momentum the anal analogous question
would be for a particle which has a
definite position does it have a
definite
momentum the answer is of course no
that's the uncertainty principle and the
same is true with angular momentum and
angle if you measure the thing and you
kick it into a state of a definite
orientation you must
have
um given a kick to its angular momentum
same kind of Heisenberg story if you
measure the position you give it a knock
and you influence its momentum if you
measure the orientation of the molecule
you affect its angular momentum but what
if the what if the spectrum of energy
levels is such that the first angular
momentum excitation is just more energy
than you have available
in
your in your photons that are doing the
measuring what if the energy to the
first excited rotational state is
gigantic for some
reason then your apparatus simply
canot resolve the
orientation so it becomes a question
given your apparatus what is the exit
how much energy does it take to excite
the first angular momentum State now for
a basketball or a dumbbell a real
dumbbell the energy separation between
the first state and the second state is
incredibly small you can figure it out
yourself there's moment of inertia
there's quantization of angular momentum
you can figure it out but the energy
level is theend the separation of energy
levels is incredibly small so it's not
surprising that with an with an ordinary
light you can measure the orientation of
the
dumbbell it doesn't take very much
energy to kick the dumbbell into a state
of Def of um of definite
orientation but for molecule the energy
levels are somewhat
spread uh the smaller the molecule if we
go from molecules for example to mesons
mesons are also dumbbells they've got
two quarks they're also
dumbbells the energy that it would take
to kick a Meson into uh into its first
excited rotational state is hundreds of
millions of yeah yeah hundreds of
millions of um electron volts maybe a
billion electron
volts that's huge by comparison with any
Optical Photon that you would try to do
an experiment with so if this were a
Meson you simply could not with ordinary
experiments resolve the fact that it's
lopsided or that it's not a sphere all
you would do is measure over and over
again the fact that on the average it's
spherical that on the average the ground
state wave
function is spherical and you keep
measuring it measuring it measuring it
and you're not going to find out it's
not a sphere until you probe it with
things which have enough energy to be
able to kick it into um into a state
like
this so the question of whether a thing
is a sphere or not is a little bit
confusing this the molecule is composed
of two things with a bridge between them
like this doesn't look like a sphere but
on the other hand the quantum mechanical
wave function spherical IES
it
okay ordinary particles if they have if
they are bons in their ground States
typically have zero angular momentum
look as spherical as it's possible to be
if they are
bons but if they're firion then they
have half spin they can't have angular
momentum
zero if they don't have angular momentum
zero it means they're not rotationally
symmetric this has nothing to do with
how the charge is
distributed it's just a fact that half
spin particles have an axis they have a
spin axis you can measure their spin
along an axis they're definitely not
spherical they definitely have a spin
axis
so quite independently of any
measurement that's done about electric
dipole moments the electron is not a
sphere the electron has or is not
spherically symmetric it has an axis the
axis is the spin
axis you have the spin
axis and about that spin axis you can
imagine a little
current there's a little electric
current that goes around the spin axis
this is a little model for the Magnetic
Moment of the electron you can think of
it as having a spin axis carrying charge
around forming a current and that
current makes it a little
electromagnet okay so it has a Magnetic
Moment definitely not
spherical uh and that should be the end
of the story about whether an electron
is a sphere or not but what did they
measure okay so once you know that the
electron has an orientation like that
and the orientation can be defined by
the direction of its Magnetic
Moment then you can ask relative to that
direction relative to that direction is
there a charge imbalance is there more
charge
on the let's call this the North and
let's call this the South it's a little
magnet it's also got electric charge you
can ask what the electric charge
distribution is if the electron is put
into a definite spin state for example
up well I didn't draw up I did some
other one here so we could ask is there
a little bit of
excess positive charge at the North Pole
and negative charge at the South Pole of
course the
overall electron is not neutral it's uh
negatively charged but on top of that is
there a displacement of the center of
charge relative to the axis along the
axis of the north south
uh um orientation of the magnet so what
we're talking about is a correlation a
correlation between the electric charge
displacement and the Magnetic
Direction that's the thing that would be
called the electric dipole moment of the
electron if you Orient the magnetic
properties of the electron the electric
the magnetic dipole or just to spin
along some axis then is there an
electric dipole moment along that axis
and that's a good question that means
something that's
measurable okay
any questions about that are you
interested I mean I'll go on a little
more about what the experiment uh yeah
so wouldn't that violate uh charge
quantization no why charge
quantization I guess I think of it in
terms of you either have a fixed charge
or you don't there's no uh freedom to
spread the charge about if the charge
were just a little bit displaced toward
the North Pole it would have a dipole
moment that's all it would take just
displace it a little little bit uh
whether you smear it or not all it would
take is a little displacement uh and so
aren't electric dipole moments uh
forbidden by uh Quantum field Theory
no no if they were nobody would be
looking for them they are forbidden by
certain
symmetries okay so let's talk about the
symmetries which forbid which would
forbid electric dipole
moment okay the first symmetry that
would forbid electric Di pole moment is
reflection symmetry reflection in a
plane now let us suppose for a moment
that the world and the laws of physics
were really reflection invariant in
other words every M mirror
image is a
possible solution of the equations of a
system and let's suppose there's only
one
electron well if the mirror image of an
electron has to be another possible
solution of the
theory okay and if there's only one
electron meaning to say one species of
electron then the mirror image must be
exactly the same as the original
electron itself there's only one
electron and it must be its own Mirror
Image okay so now let's talk about this
thing
here uh let's think about it let's put a
mirror over
here
can you see where the mirror
is okay we could also we could also
think about yeah let's think about the
uh the Blackboard is the mirror and
let's look into the Blackboard uh the
traditional way of drawing a magnetic
field into the Blackboard is to put some
tail feathers sticking out so that's the
tail end of the uh and that means that
means that the current is going around
this
way and we're asking is there an
inout
um uh imbalance of charge I guess this
is this is better this is better okay
what's the mirror image of this
configuration here the mirror image of
this configuration is another electron
which is also a pointer of some type now
the first question is where is its
Magnetic North Pole the mirror image we
have the mirror image of a
magnet where is
in the mirror image here where's the
North
Pole you think it's here don't
you the mirror image is here
again okay why is that it's because the
real thing that's going on that gives
the North Pole this is an electromagnet
the real physical phenomena that's going
on is not oriented along here it's the
current going around in the
loop the current going around in the
loop here is the real thing which is
creating the magnetic field the real
phenomenon of magnetism is associated
with loop-like currents now let's
suppose we have a looplike positive
current going around this way what's the
mirror image of
it it's a looplike current going around
in exactly the same way so the mirror
image up here as a loop going around the
same way this does and therefore the
mirror image of a magnet is a magnet
pointing in the same
direction okay now let's also suppose
that there was some charge
imbalance and let's suppose that the
charge IM balance of this electron over
here was displaced up
toward the head of the
arrow where would the charge
displacement of this one
be now just think mirror image don't
think about North South think mirror
image I have a
thing with a charge displaced toward the
mirror what's the mirror image going to
be mirr toward the mirror so the charge
displacement is going to be down here
but now we have a electron which is
different than this one its north south
is correlated in a different way with
its electric dipole moment this one had
an electric dipole moment that's along
that's that's matched in the same
direction as the Magnetic
Moment this one has an electric dipole
moment in the opposite direction if all
electrons are the same in other words if
there's only one kind of electron and if
mirror symmetry is a good symmetry if
the world is really symmetric in other
words if everything which exists it's
Mirror Image can also exist but there's
only one electron and there's only one
conclusion this charge cannot be
displaced from the
center it must be at the center so that
the mirror
images have the same
property okay that's the only way that
uh that the electron charge can be
distributed
if you have Mirror Image symmetry parody
symmetry it's called reflection symmetry
all the same thing in other words if the
world is such that the laws of physics
don't distinguish between left hand and
right
hand okay now the laws of physics do
distinguish between left hand and right
hand we know for example there are left
no there are left-hand neutrinos there
are only right-handed anti neutrinos
left and right are not the same they're
correlated with uh and
reflection symmetry is not a good
symmetry of physics so that sounds like
it opens up the
possibility of an electron dipole moment
that sounds like once you admit that the
world is not symmetric with respect to
reflection
symmetry then there's no reason why the
electron may not have a dipole
moment however there's another symmetry
which works in a very similar way
which is a much more accurate symmetry
reflection symmetry in particle physics
is bad it's not even approximately right
in the weak
interactions it's broken as bad as it
could
be there's another Symmetry and it's
time reversal it's simply the same the
statement that if you take a movie of a
uh thing and you run it backward that
that's another solution of the theory
now that may or may not be a symmetry it
may or may not be but but let's suppose
that it is let's suppose that reversing
the film is a symmetry first question
is
what
happens to the
um now we're not reflecting in a mirror
we're just reflecting in
time so let's put another electron over
here what happens on the time reversal
to the north south magnetic
momentt switches why because if a
positive current is going around this
way and you run the film backward the
positive current is going the other
way what happens to the position of the
electric charge along here if you run it
backward nothing running it backward
doesn't move the electric
charge so when you time reverse
it the nor North Pole gets down here the
South Pole gets up here but the electric
charge if it were
displaced would be displaced toward the
South Pole here and toward the North
Pole here and so again you would find
out that if if time symmetry time
reversal symmetry were a good symmetry
you could not have the electron having a
dipole moment if there was only one
electron and it looks exactly the same
as its time reversal
then the charge has to be right at the
center because the time reversal
interchanges North and South in other
words it just turns this thing over but
um but it doesn't move the
charge
yeah uh currents and charges have to be
uh reversed have to be what are are
reversed by time reversal no currents
are not
charges charges are reversed by
C doesn't uh non-relativistic quantum
mechanics uh already not time reversible
because the the operator is
anti-unitary yes but it's time
reversible because it's
anti-unitary um It's Time
reversible would couldn't all of this
whole discussion be based upon the fact
that
electrons are have a volume it's not a
point particle no no we're just asking
whether okay you don't have to if if you
want to know whether it has an electric
dipole
moment What's the experiment you do we
now have okay we put the electron into a
magnetic
field and
um no we don't put the electron in the
magnetic field we want to know whether
the the electron has a electric dipole
moment how do we find out if it has a
magnetic dipole
moment you put it in a magnetic field
and you see whether the two orientations
of the electron have different uh
different um
energy you do the same thing with a
electric field you put the electron in
an electric field and you see if the two
orientations of the spin of the electron
have different energy because of the
electric field I mean that's that's a
that's a very easy way to do it except
that that's much too hard uh
experimentally it's trickier than that
but that's the basic experiment okay
so time reversal would be enough to tell
you that the uh that the electron can't
have a dipole moment but is time
reversal a real symmetry of nature the
answer is no again in particle physics
we know that time Universal is not a
good symmetry there are processes in
even in in the standard model
model which violate time reversal
symmetry but there but the the magnitude
of the effects are very very very
tiny the magnitudes of the effect we
understand where time reversal asymmetry
comes from in the standard
model you can then do a calculation in
the standard model of the allowable
value of the electron dipole moment and
it's far to too small to be
experimentally
detected so it's never been never been
experimentally detected and if the
standard model is
right uh I don't know if it'll ever be
detected but it' be very hard to
detect they didn't detect it they
detected no dipole
moment that's good for the standard
model the only thing is that most people
don't believe in the standard model they
think that the standard model has to be
corrected by additional particles by
super Symmetry by new interactions by
new corrupting influences which
potentially could break the prim
reversal symmetry much
worse so the fact that the electron is
discovered the not has an electric
dipole moment fact that the electron
does not have a dipole moment is not an
indication that it's a
sphere it's an indication it doesn't
have an electric dipole
moment and
it makes it that much harder to
um to introduce things that that change
the standard model the standard model at
the moment describes everything we know
this was an experiment to try to detect
an effect that the standard model would
not have could not have basically is
unallowed it's allowed but it's at such
a level and it's at a computable level
which is much too small so the result is
uh that this experiment um makes it even
harder to believe in this or that um
modification of the standard model was
what was the context of the experiment
was it
a a material body or a high energy
physics experiment no no no it's a
tabletop experiment involving electrons
and magnetic fields and uh with solid
objects yeah electrons and magnetic
fields I I don't know exactly what the
experiment is I mean ordinarily you take
an electron and you put it in a field
and you let it process around the field
but
um uh for many many uh
processions no but it had enough
sensitivity to to compare with the
modifications of the standard model that
people would like to
see right
so uh it's kind of interesting I I
always love reading uh the uh the
commentary that people write in and how
confused they can be about what
uh
um yeah somebody wrote in saying well
this really proves that the standard
model is garbage and we should give it
up well exactly the opposite it's uh
it's
um
anyway how did I I don't know how I got
on
that so do that result hm does that
result um constrain in an interesting
way which modifications are potentially
viable I don't know I I I don't know you
know I haven't followed that kind of
thing in great detail somebody like sa
theopolis could probably tell you well
that the that cuts the parameter space
down by
72.1% and and
uh um but you know any experiment
which uh insists on giving results which
are consistent with a standard model to
high Precision make it that much harder
to modify
it
so uh all right let a quick question is
is time reversal Symmetry and uh
conservation of information somewhat
related or no time reversal
symmetry you always have in physics a
symmetry called
CPT that's the that's the combination
of time
reversal change the charges change the
sign of the charge and reflect in a
mirror all three of those
simultaneously uh is a symmetry always
has to be and that's enough to ensure
that um that in fact you don't even need
that to ensure that information is
conserved no you can there are systems
very familiar systems which not time
rival invariant just an electron in a
magnetic field an electron in a magnetic
field goes in circular orbits and those
circular orbits go one way or the other
depending on the sign of the magnetic
field so if you stick in a definite
magnetic field the mathematical
structure of the theory is not time
reversal and variant but this it's a
perfectly good quantum mechanical system
so just a particle in a magnetic
field uh the math mathematical structure
of the Stringer equation is not time
reversal and variant if you knew what
the magnetic field was and somebody
showed you a
um a
movie of the electron moving you could
tell instantly whether it was a movie or
an anti-m movie meaning to say that it
was going backward uh rather than
forward but of course that's only
because you didn't time with reverse
everything what did that exper the
experiment I just described electron in
a magnetic field and it goes in One
Direction what did I fail to not the
time reverse the magnetic field yeah if
I was really doing the
fullblown um time reversal symmetry I
would also have to change the sign of
the magnetic
field
yeah Okay I uh I'm sorry I don't know
how I got on all of that was not my
intention to
uh just
rambling it's called old
age let's stop for a few minutes and
then we'll get back to Second
quantization and all that
stuff mostly I wanted to rest from doing
mathematics on the
Blackboard okay we
were we were doing second
quantization and um
I thought I
would tell you a few things about it
that uh that I haven't mentioned so far
in no particular order but uh some of
the physical consequences of it the
first first thing is somebody asked me
whether the field operators and so forth
how they're connected with Foria
transforms so I thought I would tell you
to begin with exactly what the
connection with foror transforms is
um it's very
simple if you remember in ordinary
quantum mechanics you have wave
functions and the squares of the wave
functions are um probabilities to find
particles at different
places you can Foria transform the wave
function and the Foria transform is the
wave function in the momentum
basis so while s of
X this is not the field operator this is
little
s little s is the wave function for a
single
particle s of X is the wave function and
S star s Y is the
probability probability of what
probability to find the particle at
position x p of X probability of X now
supposing I want to work in the momentum
basis the momentum basis tells me what
the amplitude for the momentum to have a
certain value and if I Square it it
gives me the probability to have a
certain momentum so that's a thing
that's called I think we probably called
it side
um did we call it side
twiddle we
did side twiddle of
P the twiddle is just to make another
symbol side twidle of P where p is the
momentum that's a
thing which when you square
it is the probability but not the
probability for the particle to have a c
position but the probability to have
momentum
P this p and this P are different one is
probability one is
momentum okay what's the connection
between s of X and S twiddle of P
they're Foria conjugates of each other
or Foria transforms of each other so
let's write that down let's uh come over
here
s twiddle of p s twiddle of p is equal
to the integral over
X e to Theus I PX that's the Foria
transform it's a function of P not X
because X has been integrated over and
The Marvelous thing is that you can go
back and forth if you know what s p is
then you can reconstruct what s of X is
and so s of
X is equal to the integral
DP over sare < TK of 2
pi s twidle of
P only difference e to the plus I
PX and that's forious theorem that's
forious theorem
relating
uh functions and their fora
transforms now it has a physical
significance and the physical
significance is uh in terms of
probabilities or wave functions for
momentum and
position okay now
let's go now to the second quantization
theory where we have not a wave function
for a particle but a field operator
creation and Annihilation
operators I'm not going to prove a lot
of stuff tonight I'm going to tell you
facts but they're facts which are pretty
darn reasonable and you can reconstruct
them from what we
said Okay so let's uh let's go back to
the definition of the field field
operator now it's a field operator
capital S of X and it was originally a
sum over all
the energy igen vectors of a system of
creation operators this one would be uh
let's see this is the annihilation
operator let's call S
minus a minus of I
times s of X where this I I of X over
here is just the ordinary wave function
of a particle with State I okay we work
we we went through that a couple of
times now what if we were dealing with
the case of a free particle on an
infinite Axis or infinite whatever the
dimensionality of space is a free
particle whose energy igen states are
what just a particle moving in empty
space What are the energy igen states of
a free
particle well you can begin by asking
what's the hamiltonian and the
hamiltonian is p^2 over
2m so the igen states of energy are
likely to be igen states of momentum if
you know the momentum then you know the
energy what are the igen states or what
are the wave functions of the igen
states of
momentum they're e to the
IX okay so if we were to go to the case
of a free particle
the s i of X would
be e to the I
PX what this oh this I is different than
this I this I is the square root of
minus one over here this I is an integer
what happened to the integer here
where's the integer labeling the
momentum I states there is no integer
all there is is the momentum the
momentum states are labeled by momentum
momentum is not an integer it's a
continuous variable it goes from minus
infinity to plus infinity but it
replaces the index telling you
which igen Vector of energy you were
talking about here the igen vectors are
e to the I PX and instead of having a
sum over I you have an integral over
p and you have an nihilation
operator for a particle of momentum
P this object here removes a particle of
momentum
p in the same way that a minus removes a
particle in the state
I so if you have a state with lots of
particles in it and there are among
other things particles of momentum P if
you act with a minus it removes one
particle of momentum momentum P what if
there is no particle of momentum P there
what does it
do it just annihilates the state in the
same way that uh that Annihilation
operators uh or or lowering
operators annihilate states with nothing
in them right so that's s of
X the field operator and for good
measure as a matter of definition we put
a square root of 2 pi there
just to make it look like
um like this equation
here so it looks awfully
much like a minus of p in the
mathematical connection here is playing
the same
role as s twiddle of P
here
okay all we've done is replace Place
sums by integrals I by the momentum of
the particle and we now have the notion
of a um of an Annihilation operator for
a particle of momentum
P now do you remember what s of X did
itself not what's not what these
creation operators here did but what did
s of X do when it acts on a
uh when it acts on a
um on the vacuum for
example
sorry
oh I want the creation
piece so plus same thing except A+
here with e to the minus I
PX my knee is going okay so what does
what does um S Plus
do
it creates a particle it's got a bunch
of creation operations in it and what
kind of particle does it
create a particle at position
x a particle at position X that's what S
Plus of of X
is what do you think that a minus of P A
Plus of P
does it creates a particle with momentum
P okay so it's clear that S Plus and S
minus oh
incidentally you can um invert this
equation you can for example write that
a minus of
p is equal to
integral
DX field operator s of
X
time e to the minus I
PX again over < TK of Pi to
Pi in other words you can do do the same
manipulation as you do with forus
theorem you can prove it you can prove
one thing follows from the other and
what it says is that there's a
mathematical correspondence or
similarity between wave functions in
position and momentum space and creation
and Annihilation operators for particles
at positions or particles with given
momentum the a minus of p is essentially
the Foria is anal us I could have called
this here AF ofp I could have called
this AF
ofp just redefine instead of s twiddle
and then these formulas would look very
similar they would look
identical but all this is saying is that
the relationship between creation and
Annihilation operators for positions and
momentums creating a particle at a given
position that's done with s of X
creating a
particle uh is it this right
yeah let's do the creation part part
plus I think it's this
way
um the creation operators for particles
of given position and given
momentum are for your conjugates of each
other so that's one fact about second
quantization and keep in mind these are
not wave functions now these are
operators that operate to create and
remove
particles so I is the field operator for
a particular kind of particle if there
are several different kinds of particles
in the system then you have to have
several different kinds of field
operators there's a field operator for
each kind of
particle okay so that's one
fact that's one fact second fact and I'm
going to quote some facts now without
proof but they're all things that you
can prove from the definitions and
they're they're
straightforward
okay let's come back to the let's use
the the A+ I's instead of momentum
States
um here's something that we wrote
down for creation and Annihilation
operators uh
I do you remember what the commutator
of A+ with a minus is Del Delta i
j what about a minus with a
minus for any I and
J zero what about A+ with
A+ zero these are the only commutators
which are um
nonzero okay well I could ask a
different question I could ask instead
what are the commutators of size of X at
different positions instead of
asking what are the commutation
relations between the creation operators
and Annihilation operators in the basis
I and J I could ask what is the
commutator of the creation operator for
a particle at point
x with the annihilation
operator at point
Y
we you that's right okay but how would
you how would you prove it you would
prove it by simply sticking in the
definition of the size in terms of the
creation and Annihilation operators and
then using the commutation relations of
the creation and Annihilation operators
and what you would find is exactly what
was just said it's just Delta of xus
Y in other words they
commute
when the points are not the same and
they don't commute and they with a very
big
noncommut remember a Delta function has
the property that it's infinite at the
uh when X is equal to
Y so the commutators of s s plus and S
minus have this Delta function in them
what about S Plus with
s+ that's just made out of creation
operators and all creation operators
commute
likewise for S minus so the only things
which don't commute are S Plus with s
minus now we could a we could we've
mentioned several times I think that the
size because they're complex because
they're not Herm Mission are not
observables this is true but it's not a
very interesting point because the sum
of S Plus with s minus is an observable
and the differences time I are
observables so let's this is not a
particularly interesting
fact uh question yeah I'm just curious
um what does that mean when xal y it
means that it's very large everywhere no
yeah and for any X whenever X is equal
to Y it's large no no suppose you put in
oh okay I yeah yeah okay now let's let's
ignore the fact for the moment that uh
that these
are not observables the real and
imaginary parts are observables and
what's true is the commutator of the
real part with the imaginary part is
also a Delta function like this point is
a Delta function and uh it's it's not so
interesting that these things are not
Herm Mission you can always make them
her Mission by adding uh real and
imaginary Parts okay so what does it say
what what is the consequence of two
things not
commuting you know any examples of two
of operators which don't
commute X and P right X and P are the
standard examples of operators that
don't commute X and P the commutator is
IH bar how about um Sigma you know the X
component of a spin and the Y component
of a spin they don't commute either the
commutator is the Z component of spin
what's the
physical significance of not
commuting as far as doing measurements
is
concerned you can't do simultaneous
measurements of the same thing or
another way of saying it is the
measurement of one of them gives a kick
to the other one trying to measure the
Precision trying to measure with
Precision the position of a particle
necessarily gives it a hard kick and
destroys
the measurement of the momentum or makes
the measurement of the momentum very
uncertain measuring a momentum very
precisely spreads the position all over
the place but let's just say that it
introduces Mutual
uncertainty Mutual uncertainty of the
kind the Heisenberg kind where when
measuring one thing interferes with a
measurement of another
thing all right now this is a very
interesting fact here let's forget for
the fact let's forget for the moment the
Delta function when X is equal to Y
let's talk about when X does not equal y
when X does not equal y it says that
these things commute okay this is very
very plausible it says that the
measurement of a field over here does
not interfere with the measurement of a
field over here if I measure the
electric field this this could be the
electric electromagnetic field it's a
little bit different and we're we're
going to come through it but if we get
time but it's a field it's a field what
this says is measuring the field at one
place does not interfere with measuring
the field at another place you can
measure a field over here and here
simultaneously and there's no Mutual
uncertainty in them okay even infinitely
close no when you get right on top of
each
other
then measuring the real and imaginary
Parts at the you can replace this here
commutator
by the real part and the imaginary part
do not
commute measuring the real part and the
imaginary part these two
observables you cannot measure them
simultaneously at the same
point okay and they interfere with each
other trying to measure one gives an
enormous wallup to the other
one and but and that's of course
interesting it's telling of something
important but the more important thing
right now is that you don't have any
interference in measurements if they're
at different places and of course that's
very very logical I mean that makes
sense particularly we're not doing
relativity Theory now we're not doing
relativity Theory but imagine that we
were the same basic principle is true in
relativity
Theory supposing it were true that
making a measurement over here
interfered with and did something over
here at the same instant of time to the
possibility of making a measurement at a
at a distant point supposing this
commutator were not zero in fact let's
suppose the commutator were big for some
reason that uh that the commutator of a
field over here and here were big what
that would say is trying to measure the
field over here gives the field a kick
over here makes it impossible to measure
it because it gives it a kick over here
well I think that would violate your
sense of uh of causality or your sense
of
locality that Einstein tells us that
signals should not propagate faster than
the speed of light somebody over here
trying to measure the field and get and
finding that he can't do it because it's
not commuting with something over
here uh violates some notion of
independence of measurements at
different
places in particular if we take two
places in times which are such that
light could not go from one to the other
the space like separated from each other
then we would be in a very confusing
situation where measuring a thing over
here and a thing over here wouldn't
commute would interfere with each other
and that seems to violate the spirit of
uh of information or perturbations or
signals or
um
uh effects do not propagate faster than
the speed of light and that's true okay
isn't that what epr experiments already
show the what um that the effect of a
measurement over here has has a uh
consequence for a measurement over there
oh
boy
no
what no entangle the the the most
fundamental thing about entanglement is
it does not tell you that making a
measurement over here has an influence
over here well I didn't say influence I
said cor I meant correlation yeah I know
but we're talking about
influence we're talking about making a
measurement over here giving a sudden
kick to something over here that's
exactly what doesn't happen where
because of entanglement measuring
something over here does not give a
thing a kick over here because of
entanglement it can only give a kick
over here and the reason why is because
things at one place commute with things
at another place that's exactly the
reason why entanglement doesn't uh send
influences faster than the speed of
light because all the degrees of freedom
at one point commute with the degrees of
freedom of someplace else and that means
they behave
independently correlation is different
than
influence
um so what this says this is good this
says that there's no
violation of your naive ideas or maybe
they're not so naive but your
straightforward ideas about the
independence of measurements at
different points of
space now of course
um uh we're not doing relativity but
nevertheless it's still a true thing
here we're going to come next time to
firion fion are fields or fion are
particles which do not satisfy any of
this in fact they satisfy a different
algebra with
anti-commutation tell you that things
are independent and measurements are
independent fermans the fields anti-c
commute at different points they don't
commute
if they don't commute that means you
can't measure them simultaneously at two
different points no matter how far away
a measurement of a of a firion field at
one place gives a sudden kick to its
complex conjugate arbitrarily far
away that sounds
crazy uh
or firon fields are not
observables there's no way that you can
construct what it's telling you really
it there's no way that you can construct
a device to measure a firon field why
because that device would have to be
spread all over space and be extremely
non-local that's what we're going to
take up next time firon operators firon
operators are the operators which create
and annihilate
electrons boson operators are the
operators which create and annihilate
photons so we'll come next time to the
firon version of second quantization
okay and uh do that okay good I'm I'm
thankful that nobody uh forced me into
doing any mathematics tonight well we
did a little
bit for more please visit us at
stanford.edu